all right so we've been learning
JavaScript and we've been learning
computer programming at the same time so
far we've covered variables if-else
statements and comparison operators next
up we're going to learn functions
functions at first to a new programmer
can feel a little tricky but I promise
you they'll catch on a lot faster than
it feels like at the very beginning so
stick with it and do what we do in this
exercise a couple days in a row and
you're going to feel pretty confident
with what functions are before we get
into functions let's move javascript
into our web page because we don't want
to be writing functions in the console
it's too many lines it would be too
annoying so here we go we're on our
index.html file and if you're going to
insert CSS on your page there's two ways
to do it you can do a style tag and then
anything within the style tags is
treated as CSS or you can pull in an
external style sheet another file with a
link tag JavaScript works the same way
we can run a script tag and then
anything within this script tag is
treated as JavaScript I'm going to say
alerts and I'm also going to hit save
and I'm running what's called live
reload so when I save my file this web
browser is going to automatically reload
my page if you're doing this bonheur on
your own without live reload you're
going to have to save and then hit
refresh if you want to see how I'm doing
live reload I'll put some links to that
in the description but it might be a
little over your head if you're a brand
new user so there you go you can see
that now my web page when it reloads has
alerted of empty alert for me and
there's a reason I put the script tag at
the bottom of the page and let me show
you why by moving it up towards the top
I'm gonna hit save again and you'll
notice that now I get the alert before I
see my webpage I have an empty page and
the alert fires this happens because
JavaScript happens in sequence as your
webpage is rendering all the elements
what that means is is when your browser
opens up your HTML file it's going to
start going through line by line and
adding in all the elements so when it
gets to a script tag it's going to load
all that javascript and then it's going
to run it before it does anything else
so in this case it runs my alert up here
before it's rendered
all these elements onto the page you
know javascript is really pretty fast
you're not really doing alerts a lot so
all the user will normally notice if you
put your script at the top of the page
is the webpage might feel like it
appears a little bit slower if you put
it down here at the bottom of the page
right before the closing body tag then
what's going to happen is is your
webpage will spit out all the content
first so it looks like the web page is
loaded and a split second later your
script will be activated and web
developers have learned over the years
that this creates a much faster feeling
web page and the user doesn't know any
difference so we recommend they always
put your script tags at the bottom right
before your closing body tag there's
almost never a reason that your script
needs to go in the top up in the header
so the script tag is the first way of
doing it and just like a link tag you
can also give the script tag a file to
pull in as well so in this case I'm
going to delete the content and I'm just
going to go source SRC equals and then
that basically is like the href is for
CSS so instead of pulling in the Styles
main CSS I'm going to pull in the
scripts main j/s and now that file gets
loaded in and executed as soon as it's
loaded the normal folder name for
javascript is going to be called a j/s
folder or a scripts folder so here we
have scripts j/s is just fine either one
works so now I'm loading in this main
dot JS file so if I hit alerts and save
you see I get that alert as well and
it's already rendered my web page first
before it's executing my JavaScript so
there's how you get JavaScript on a page
if you have multiple JavaScript files
you can do multiple script tags just
like that and it will execute them in
order it's going to run my main TAS
first then my main dot two then my main
dot three then my main dot four so
that's what's going to happen if you
have multiple script tags if you want to
break up your JavaScript into several
files to make it easier to maintain so
let's go ahead and learn now functions
so functions are basically a piece of
code that does one or more actions peace
of code that does one or more actions so
I'll just show you what a function is
because it's a lot easier to see it than
to hear about it
you start off by typing function and
we'll just call this function go you
open and close your parentheses and then
you open and close your curly braces so
whatever I put in here is going to
execute when the go function is called
so let's just say alert I alert hey
there and so it's going to do two alerts
I'm going to save my webpage refresh is
and guess what nothing happens because I
defined my ko function but I didn't call
my NGO function I call it by saying go
open closed parenthesis and then a
semicolon now when i refresh it's going
to say hi and then it's going to say hey
there I have my function a cool thing
about functions is they can be called as
many times as you want I can call go
twice hi hey there hi hey there so
that's kind of cool another thing about
functions is they accept what are called
arguments let me show you what arguments
are I could say name age and then
instead of alerting hi hey there
I can alert name and I can alert age now
in order for it to know what the name in
the age are I pass them in when I'm
calling my function so I can say my name
is Will and I'm 34 because I just had a
birthday so now will gets passed in as
the first argument which is name and 34
gets passed in is a second argument
which is age so now it's going to alert
will and then it's going to alert 34
let's save it there you go will there
you go 34 once again these are called
arguments and what arguments allow us to
do is they allow us to make code
reusable because at first you might
think hmmm I could just stick to go I
could go there name equals will and then
their age equals 34 and then I could
forget this whole arguments thing and I
could just say alert name age well yep
that's going to do the same thing it's
going to alert will and it's going to
alert 34 but if I code it with arguments
its reusable let me show you let's go
back to name age
let's go back to will 34 and now I can
call it a second time with a different
person let's say my wife Laura 28 there
we go so now it's going to run one time
with will and 34 will 34 and then the
next time it runs it's going to run with
Laura 28 and so that's kind of a good
way of coding it's it's called dry which
is do not repeat yourself
if I get spell do not repeat yourself dr
y do not repeat yourself or don't repeat
yourself so dry code is a good thing we
want to code as little as possible that
makes it easy to maintain that makes for
as few lines of code as possible so
that's kind of what a function does it
accepts arguments and it runs multiple
commands now a function also returns a
value whatever you type in return will
actually give you a value out let me
show you what a return value does you
might remember from prompt earlier in
the first lesson we went very name
equals prompts and then prompt opened up
a window I'll just show you right there
it opened up a window and then when I
said will enter will got passed in from
the prompt into my name variable so what
actually happened was is prompt had a
return value that name received you see
that it executed this first and when
prompt was done whatever prompt returned
which was my name will went into name
and so how you code a function like that
is very simple let's make a function
called add and let's make it first
second we want to add two numbers
together and so I'm going to go add
let's say their sum equals add one and
two so we're going to add one into
together and so instead of just going
first plus second I'm going to return
first plus second so now nothing
actually
happens in this function like alerts or
anything like that we are going to
return the value of first plus second
which means it's going to run the
function the function executes it
returns kicks back out first plus second
which means that it's going to add one
and two and then that is going to get
passed into some so now I can alert some
and sum is going to be three there you
go three because I added one and two it
returned that back out so I could do
something silly like this I could pass
in add one and two that's one that's two
I'm just going to return will so now
it's just going to say well some equals
will and I alerted to I basically
ignored my arguments I returned whatever
value I wanted to return which didn't
make any sense and that value got passed
into here so now now no matter what I
pass into ad function it's always going
to return we'll of course again that's
kind of silly I want to return one plus
two and now I have my ad function
another way that you can do this with a
little bit less code is I could just
alert add one and two so it's going to
run this first because this is an inner
function javascript is going to know I
have to run this in order to know what
to give to alert whatever this returns
I'm going to pass into my alert function
as the value so this will do the exact
same thing it's going to run one and two
one and two returns three and then as
far as JavaScript is concerned it's just
going to alert that returned value so
I'm going to save that you see it alerts
three let me show you what happens if
you alert if you return a second time
let's return will now it does absolutely
nothing because as soon as the return
happens this function is finished what
happens after the return never fires
javascript is done so I can say alerts
hi there and you're never going to see
alert hi there it alerts three from down
here and I never see the alert hi there
up here the function ran
it returned and then the function was
finished now you can have multiple
returns you could do something like hmm
let's go their name equals we'll say
this let's go alert add add is kind of a
bad it will call will go back to go
since we're not going to be doing adding
will and we'll go back to my age of 34
so this is going to be now called go
name age if age is less than 20 then we
are going to return name plus an
exclamation mark because after all in
less than 20 that's pretty cool else we
are just going to return my name so now
this will return a different thing if my
age is less than 20 then I'm going to
return name shouted else I'm going to
return just my name so go now we'll
check this out and it's just going to
return my name because I'm older than 20
and then I'm going to alert that there
you go just will so let's change my name
to 19 and now it's going to shout my
name
so after all you shout at teenagers a
lot more than you do at adults and what
happens if I don't return anything at
all let's say I say go name and age and
I'm going to get undefined so this
function has no return which means it's
returning nothing which means it's
returning undefined which brings us to
one more of our types in JavaScript and
that is the undefined type if I say
there a but I don't give it a value then
I alert a it's going to alert undefined
I define a as a variable but I didn't
define the value of a so another type in
JavaScript is undefined and it means
simply well undefined so that's about
all you need to know with that so by
default every function is going to
return undefined unless you give it a
return value
we'll again so there you go that's
functions let's um let's leave it there
for now so I'm going to say go ahead
make an addition function make a
subtraction function make a
multiplication function make some
functions play around with them and once
you feel confident with that let's move
on to our last lesson before we get into
some actual useful things that we can
use JavaScript for on our web page