hi guys this is Amer today I'm gonna be
talking about call back versus promises
most people ask about what is the
difference between these two concepts in
JavaScript are a node GS that is the
framework of JavaScript you might be
confused with call back and promises and
who in what scenarios we should use a
call back versus a promises so I'll be
giving you examples that what is the
difference between these two in which
situation we need to decide whether we
want to use a call back or we want to
use a promise so let's get started and
write the code before writing the code I
want to let all of you know that if you
want to buy a book related to JavaScript
and that is a really good book I'm gonna
give the link of this book in the
description below if you want to learn
the more advanced java script with
examples then this is a really good book
and that includes a really good examples
for you to learn even if you already
know javascript that will really help
you in learning more advanced concepts
of JavaScript so first of all I will
talk about callback in JavaScript so far
callback we need to define functions and
each function will execute
asynchronously and the second function
will be dependent on the first function
and the third function will be dependent
on the second function and so on let me
write an example that I'll explain you
what it all about so first of all we
need to define a function so I'm gonna
define three functions that can be any
number of functions like function first
and that takes a value and takes a
callback so I'm gonna copy this function
and I'm gonna paste it two more times
and I'm going to change the name of
these functions to second and third okay
so now what I want to do is I want to
call the first function and unless it
doesn't return me a nice
cific result or a response I don't want
my second function to be called and
similar for the third function so I will
use a callback for making it dependent
on each other so first of all I will
call first function and I will send it a
value so let's say I'm sending a dove
value to and after that I need to send
it a function as a parameter so function
first result and if there is an error so
what it means that I'm sending out to
two will be received in this value and
this whole function will be sent to this
callback parameter all right and using
this callback parameter that can be
anything I've just written it called
back that is more meaningful using this
callback parameter I can return the
value that can be received within this
first result and then I can send out a
boolean whether it's a error or not so
let me return like callback and the
first value is value plus two and after
that I need to send out if there is an
error or not so there is no error okay
so in here I am checking if there is an
error if there is no error then call the
second function so I'm copying this
first function and after that I'm
calling my second function and I am
receiving the second result and in the
second function I'm sending out the
first result okay so just copy it and
paste it call the third function
and I will receive a third result from
here and inside it I will check the
result
so third result okay so I'm gonna copy
these callback statements okay so that's
it now what it is doing first of all I'm
sending out to two is being received
within this value and inside this first
function I'm using this callback this is
a being refer to a function okay and
using this function called back I am
adding to within the value and returning
this value and this boolean value in
that callback function okay and then
inside this function I'm checking out if
there is an error if there is no error
then I'm calling out the second function
okay and inside the second function
I am sending out the result of the first
callback function okay and that will be
received here and again I am adding up
two and calling back and that callback
will send out these two values in the
callback function of this second
function and that will be received in
the second result and error and I'm
checking out if there is no error that
I'm calling out the third function and
that can reach up to unlimited number of
functions okay so the purpose of doing
it in this way is that if there is there
I'm just adding up these two value and
that takes no time okay but what if we
are calling a server cause we are
calling an API and we are fetching out a
very big data that is actually take some
time so and that data is need for this
second function okay so I have called
the second function within the first
function
it means that unless and until the first
function doesn't return a specific value
right here don't call this second
function and if the second function this
callback of the second function doesn't
return the result right here then until
and unless don't call the third function
and same goes further okay and same for
the third function of force function or
fifth function or we can call a hundreds
of functions like this okay so let's try
it let's dry run it first of all I'm
sending out two that will be four
folders will be received right here and
four is sent out right here 4 plus 2 6
and 6 will be received here and 6 is
going to send out here and that will be
add up here and that will be become it
and then it should be printed right here
so let's check out the result whether
it's working or not so I'm going to
click on run and run script yes I'm
using webstorm you might be using other
IDE that can be other that can have
other way to run the scripts but I have
this way in webstorm so let's click on
run script and go to terminal and you
can see it has shown me the result 8 and
that is correct okay so let me first try
and give you an overview that how it is
working so first result and I'm copying
this line and Here I am sending out the
second result ok so now let's run it
again so now you can see it has printed
4 6 8 and you can see that first is
printed the 4 and it didn't print the
result of the second function before the
result of the first function because the
second function calling is dependent on
the result of the first function so that
is like if we want to face the data from
a server like we want to face the
all the tweets are from Twitter and that
tweets needs to be saved in database so
we can't save an empty data to the
database first we need to verify whether
the all the data have been fetched from
the Twitter and if the all the data have
been fetched from the Twitter then we
will save that data to the database so
that is really helpful to use the
callback function so now let's talk
about promises let me give you an
example then I will compare callback and
promises and give you an idea of what to
use when and what is good for you people
to use in various scenarios okay so I'm
going to comment this much code okay and
below that I'm going to use these same
functions with the help of promises in
fact I won't be commenting this these
functions I'll be just commenting this
first this usage of these three
functions okay so right here there are
many ways to use the promises in
JavaScript and nodejs there are various
modules available extensions available
that provide promises but right now in
JavaScript I will just give you an
overview using a promise constructor
function that is pretty basic and the
general usage of promises and that is
very easy to understand and I just want
to give you guys an idea that what is
promises and how to use it okay
so now first of all I need to create a
variable of a promise using a
constructor promise function so I will
use promise equals to new promise and it
needs a function and that returns a
result and reject
and for returning the data from within
the promise we need to use this resolved
parameter and that is actually the
function calling so inside
Eid let's return to okay so by using
this promise we can execute a function
or multiple functions so let's execute
only one function first and see whether
it's working or not
so using this promise dot then and
function and response and inside it
let's bring the response right now I'm
not calling the first second and third
function so these are just a return here
these are not being used right now so
let's save this file and I'm going to
click on run and run script and you can
see it has printed - okay so what it is
doing is using this promise variable it
is using this then function make sure
and remember that if you are using a
constructor promise function and in most
of the cases most people use the same
technique of using promises they use
then it means that don't call don't
execute this function that is within the
then function unless and until this
promise return the result okay and when
this promise will Reiser return the
result when this resolve will be caught
and we can call a server call inside it
we can call a database call we can call
any kind of API right now it not take
any time but if you are calling a server
call that might take time so we need to
add promises inside it or even we can
use callbacks inside the promises as
well okay so now let's create and use
these more functions inside these
promises so first of all let me
remove this control double yolk response
and I'm going to use this function okay
so so I'm going to remove this function
and before using these functions let me
remove the callback because we are using
promises so we don't need call back
right here and instead of these
callbacks we need to return these values
okay so let's copy this line and copy
here and copy here okay so now let's use
this promise dot then and we need to
call the functions so then first dot
then second dot then third dot then and
function and response and console dot
log and response okay so let's run it
and you can see it has printed eight so
let me explain you how is it working so
promise dot then and I'm using this
function and it is calling this function
I'm not sending out any value inside it
instead it will automatically receive
the value from the previous function
right here the previous result of this
promise is this this promise this
function and whatever will be returned
from this resolve is becoming the
parameter that is going to be sent from
within this then and this first function
okay so this is being sent out to right
here and then two plus two equals to 4
and then 4 is being used in the second
function and then four three is being
received here 4 plus 2 equals to 6 and
it is called
third and third is receiving 6 and then
6 plus 2 equals to 8 and then 8 is being
received within this response and that
response is being logged out and that's
why you have seen that result 8
ok so let's compare the callbacks and
the function we are executing the same
kind of functionality using the
callbacks and the functions we can also
use before returning right here we can
also use callback function we can use
the promises within the callbacks or a
callback within the promises so it's up
to us that how we want to use it ok we
need to use a callback right here if
within this first function we need to
fight the data from somewhere that will
take time so we don't want to return the
value from here until it it it receives
the data from that server ok so we need
to wait for the server to send the data
and then we will receive we can return
the data within that callback function
okay so right here let me bring it up a
bit
so in callback we use this bunch of code
right here but in promises we just wrote
this function so you can see that the in
promises we have the minimal lines of
code and that is more cleaner and in
callbacks that becomes more messy and
that is very difficult to understand if
we want to see and revise our code after
a few months then we must be able to
remember it that what I did and right
now these are just three callbacks but
in real-time applications we might have
20 plus or the 50 plus callback
functions within the other function so
that will become really messy and that
messiness is generally known as callback
hell so contact hell lead us to the
promises and that forced us to use the
promises because promises are more
cleaner and more easy to remember
or easy to revise in the future okay so
that's why if we want to use promises or
if we want to call
so many functions that are dependent on
the other function results then it is
recommended that we can use promises and
we need to use promises we can also use
callbacks but that will not be a good
practice for other people who are your
team members who want to see the code
that will be difficult for them to get
the idea what is happening here so that
is the actually reason both are the
things are saying both perform the same
functionality there is nothing that a
callback can do that a promise can't do
and same as the promise there is nothing
that promise can do that a callback
can't do so it's up to you it's up to us
that how we want to use both the things
we can merge both the things so but we
want to follow the best practices and
make our code more cleaner and more
good-looking so that's it for this video
I hope that you have liked it if you
have any question just comment below and
I just want to remember you that in the
next video I will be talking about
asynchronous programming in node.js and
that will be very helpful for you guys
who wants to write asynchronous nowadays
and many things is asynchronous so we
need to learn that what are the best
practices of writing asynchronous code
using node so wait for it make sure to
subscribe my channel don't forget to
subscribe that is really helpful for us
that really support us that encouraged
us to create more and more new videos
thanks for watching stay tuned