okay good morning welcome to my talk
about Night Watch which is a testing
framework written in JavaScript designed
for web developers a little bit about me
my name is Seth McLaughlin I am a mostly
a front-end engineer I work a little bit
on the on the backend as well while I
was at LinkedIn for a couple years I
worked on a couple of different testing
frameworks we developed a framework
called Venus jeaious which is more
focused on unit testing JavaScript code
which is not what we're talking about
today I mean I also worked on the
central QA team where I helped out with
some of the core selenium testing
infrastructure for LinkedIn and
currently I'm working for a company
called shape security we're a web
security startup based out of Mountain
View so the topic of today of course is
Nightwatch
so what is Nightwatch it is a project
implemented with nodejs and it basically
allows you to write functional tests so
just a quick show of hands how many
people are either QA engineers or write
functional tests today for their job
great and out of out of you guys how
many of you actually use javascript to
implement those tests ok good number do
you guys use Nightwatch ok not not as
many a couple ok cool so this morning I
want to talk about three main things
we're going to do a quick project
overview just to introduce Nightwatch
for those of you who maybe haven't heard
of it or aren't familiar with where it
came from and I'll list out some of the
features it supports so you can kind of
compare that against other tools that
you may be using today and finally I
want to show you some code samples to
give you a flavor of what it feels like
to write tests with Nightwatch and how
you can go ahead and actually just start
it yourself if you're curious check it
out so first let's talk a little bit
about what exactly is end-to-end testing
most of you are probably familiar but
just in case you're not intend testing
is designed to allow you as a developer
or as a test engineer
to write automated tests which capture
users interactions with your website so
for example you might be testing that a
user can log into your website so this
level of testing is very I would say
blackbox in that you don't really care
or understand how need to understand how
the code works you're basically just
automating a browser to go through the
same actions that a user would take when
they're interacting with your website
and it's really useful to automate this
because you know say you're working on a
web app every time you deploy you don't
want to have to test these scenarios
over and over again manually you much
rather be able to just run an automation
suite maybe even automatically run it in
all the major browsers you support like
Firefox you know Chrome Internet
Explorer and get some results that gives
you confidence that you can deploy and
there's no problem with your with your
app so in this case if we were testing a
login flow it might we might define it
as these six steps we might say okay
first we have to open the browser and
navigate to the login page
second we locate a form field the
username field and we type in a user
third we locate the password field type
in a password value fourth we submit the
button we click the submit button to
submit the form we wait for that form
submission to complete perhaps it's a
page load perhaps you know it's an ajax
request and then you verify some aspect
of the state of the resulting page to
ensure that your action succeeded now in
this example I'm just verifying that the
page title changed but you could verify
that certain content is in the DOM or
any number of things which would be the
success criteria for your test
so looking at a high-level architectural
overview of how this stuff works
working backwards from the right we have
the web browser of course which is being
scripted to perform these actions as a
real user would then we have something
called selenium webdriver which is a
tool which allows you to control the
browser and it's interesting that this
started out as a as a kind of a third
party approach where there's different
drivers that control different browsers
but webdriver itself is actually
becoming a w3c spec so all major
browsers should support it natively
which will be good because that'll be
just probably a lot smoother interaction
than what we've seen in the past but
today you can use webdriver with all the
major browsers and additionally Internet
Explorer 12 supports webdriver natively
which is which is great I believe
they've back ported it to IE 11 as well
and told the spec will be finalized next
I think not quite sure is this year or
next year but it's making really good
progress and then so the next step is
you have a testimony and this is what
Nightwatch rides for you so this is
something that will reading a test and
then issue commands over HTTP to
selenium which then gets translated into
actual commands to control the browser
so these different parts that I've
highlighted in the dotted lines could
actually live on different systems and
often do okay so Nightwatch itself like
I mentioned is giving you these two
components on the left so it gives you
an API for writing your tests and your
tests are actually just node modules so
if you're already familiar with node
it's pretty trivial to implement a basic
test and then the test Runner itself is
a node.js application which you can
easily install with an NPM install
it's important to note that not
surprisingly Nightwatch will also work
with selenium grid if you're familiar
with slam testing you've probably either
used grid or know what it is but
essentially what it allows you to do is
manage a pool of browsers so then you
can when you start up a test your test
runner just talks to the grid and says
hey I want to run my test with a node
that has these capabilities like it
could be I want Chrome where I want I II
or Firefox or I want this version of
Windows to run the test so what does
Nightwatch offer you first of all I
think it has fairly good documentation
it could of course always be improved so
if you're interested in this stuff I
highly encourage you to jump in and help
make it better but the author has done a
really good job of getting a baseline of
documentation I think if you go to
Nightwatch the Nightwatch website you'll
have all you need there to get started
when you're actually interacting with
your page you can use either CSS or
XPath selectors which is great because
if you're a web developer you already
know CSS and it's pretty easy to script
those tests the test Runner itself can
execute tests either sequentially or in
parallel so parallel execution is nice
because it just speeds up the process of
running all of your tests and then you
have some control over which tests get
run so you may have a large corpus of
tests maybe a thousand different tests
but you only want to run a subset of
those on every every build or every
release or something like that
so you can you can either select to run
tests by powder matching the file name
you can organize your tests into folders
or even more flexibly you could add tags
to your tests and then say okay I'm
going to tag you know test a B and C as
sanity so I always run those tests for
example I think this is pretty much
expected in this day and age but also
integrates with cloud providers like
sauce labs and browser stack so this is
really great because if you're a small
small team or a small company and you
don't have the internal resources to
setup your own test lab that's running
all these different OSS with all these
different browser versions you can sort
of outsource that to sauce labs and
they'll
provide any browser you want basically
to run your tests
it also features j-unit xml formatting
for test results which is pretty
standard so if you're using a continuous
integration system like Hudson or
Jenkins for example they can already
read this test format so it's very easy
to integrate Nightwatch with your
existing workflow and finally there is
an extension model so if there's a
particular API or feature that you don't
see in Nightwatch you can go ahead and
implement that yourself and there's
fairly good documentation around that
and I'll show a couple of examples of
doing of doing that just that so who
created Nightwatch so it was created by
a guy named Andre he actually lives in
Norway and he started working on this
project as far as I can tell about about
two years ago but it really seems like
it picked up speed in late 2013 he goes
by the name of beat factor and if you're
interested in learning more about what
he does he's a friend developer and you
can check out his LinkedIn profile which
I've linked to at the bottom here so a
couple of quick stats looking at NPM we
can see that it's fairly popular we've
got nine thousand downloads roughly last
month it's not huge not anything
compared to mocha or some other testing
libraries but I think it's definitely
growing I gave this talk last June and
at that point in time that got about
5,000 downloads a month so we're
definitely seeing a trend towards
adoption a lot of stars on github a lot
of Forks a fairly good code coverage
which is important you'd probably expect
that coming from you know a test
framework should be tested right and
it's also under active development we
can see at the bottom here that it was
last updated five days ago couple more
stats you know a fair number of
contributors there's a fairly healthy
you know pull request activity there's
one that's kind of been hanging around
for a while you know a bunch of opening
issues people are using the tool filing
issues and issues are getting fixed so
that's always good to see in an open
source project that you're thinking
about adopting because you want if
you're gonna actually use this you know
at your at your job you want to make you
want feel like it's being supported and
you'll have somewhere to go to get help
if you run into issues or just want new
features add it to a tool so drilling a
little bit more on contribution activity
as like I mentioned it's really more in
late 2013 where stuff really happened it
looks like maybe Andrzej created the
repo back in 2012 and then really just
let it sit dormant for quite a while but
in late 2013 it really picked up speed
and there's been a lot of activity ever
since I've helped out a little bit with
the project I implemented the test
tagging feature but you can see from the
commits that is predominantly Andrzej
writing the code for now ok so going
back to our simple example let's look at
how we would actually implement a
functional test to to test this user
scenario of logging into a website so
first thing we'll look at is our project
directory structure so you could of
course if you're if you're already
building your web app as a node.js app
you could just store your test files in
the same repo or same directory
structure as your project I personally
like to separate it out so my projects
start pretty simple like this you have a
Nightwatch JS file and that's your
configuration which we'll look at in a
minute and then you have a test folder
and then the test folder this is where
you put your well your tests right so
let's look at login j/s which is going
to test that login scenario for us
so like I mentioned earlier a test is
simply a node.js module so very simple
you just create this object and you can
give it a descriptive name if you'd like
like for example here I use the name
fill out form and login and that is just
a function which accepts this object
from the framework called client and
client is what you call to interact with
the browser essentially so first off I'm
using this API here URL which allows me
to direct the browser to load this web
page and then I'm doing an assertion to
say I expect something so I expect the
page title to equal this string awesome
app and this is where I'm going to
interact with the form so I'm setting a
value and then the first parameter is
the CSS selector why or I tell it you
know which field I want to operate on
and the second parameter is the value so
I want to set that field to the value of
Seth I do the same thing for the
password field and that happens click
API so I can very easily just click an
element on the page and again using a
CSS selector to locate that element and
then finally I assert that after the
page has has loaded or the form has been
submitted that now the page title is
welcome which is what I expect it to be
when I've successfully logged in and
finally it's important to call end and
that tells Nightwatch that you're done
with the test so it can close the
browser and doing kind of cleanup that
it needs to do so pretty straightforward
so one thing that's interesting this
trips up a lot of people especially if
you've come from maybe using Python Ruby
for doing this type of testing all of
these API calls are asynchronous so I've
seen this a lot where people will you
know basically send all these commands
and then at the end do something like
you know console dot log or some other
operation and they expect that console
dot log will be will be executed after
all the previous commands that executed
and that's not actually the case because
what's going on here is every time we
call client and calling API and client
is basically queuing up that that action
so way to get around this is that Andre
recently added a perform API so you call
client dot perform and that takes a
function and then you can do something
inside of that function and then that
way the console dot log will be queued
up to run after the cert ran before it
and you also have this done callback
that you can call to let the framework
know when you're done executing so for
example we might want to I don't know
get some dynamically generated value for
our test
that's an async operation so we can do
that and then when we're done we just
simply call done to continue the flow
the execution flow of the test
okay so next let's let's look at the
Nightwatch JS file which is our
configuration
so there's a lot of stuff in here
there's actually quite a few more
options that I'm not showing on this
slide but the docs have very good
documentation for all these options so
if you check out Night Watch JSC org you
can find a great reference for this
stuff but just touching on a couple of
them probably arguably one of the most
important options is telling the
framework where your tests are located
so in my directory structure I put my
tests under the folder named tests but
that's arbitrary you could store them
wherever you want to the I specifying
output folder which is where my results
will be stored and here I define some
information about the selenium so
Nightwatch itself does not come with the
selenium jar but it will start it for
you automatically if you wanted to and
to do that you have to tell it where the
jar file lives on disk so this is where
I'm doing that you can also specify
where this excuse me where the selenium
log path would go and a few other things
about selenium and here we can define
our test settings and each section
inside of this this block so default
would be considered what's called the
environment so I could have multiple
environments set up in my configuration
here I'm just configuring one
environment but I can tell it for
example you know where to find selenium
in this case I'm running it locally so
I'm just using one two seven zero zero
one but it could be running on a
different box and I can tell it some
things about where to store screenshots
and probably most importantly here I can
tell it where or excuse me
which browser I want to use so in this
case I'm using Firefox okay so that's
great but how do we actually run our
tests so that's also fairly simple you
install Nightwatch you can either
install it globally in this case that's
what I've done or you can install up to
your local project directory if you're
familiar with NPM to install globally
you just do MPM install - JEE Nightwatch
and that would get installed and so I
run Nightwatch I use the - C option to
tell it where the config file is and
then I tell it which environment I
want to use from that config file and if
I wanted to I could specify the the test
tags to run or you know other options
about which tests to run but here I'm
just running everything basically
so what's that once that runs you'll get
some nice console output where I'll show
you the name of the test suite login and
that's just derived from the file name
itself and then each test within that
suite will be will be printed with
results so here I have my fill out form
and login test and each assertion that I
made is printed out and then a green
checkmark is displayed since that
assertion passed and at the end it'll
tell me how many assertions passed and
also how long it took to run the entire
test
okay so going back to our first example
anybody that's sort of familiar with
writing tests can you tell me what what
what we might want to change about how
we wrote this test like is this this is
a good way to write tests
is there any no anti patterning that you
can see here before range before each o
for test test hook see yeah you could
you could do that but what I'm talking
about in particular is these values so
they're hard-coded right which isn't
super flexible one common scenario might
be like say you're testing a large site
I mean we did this at LinkedIn for
example so every time you run a test you
might want to have an API where you call
to get a valid set of user credentials
so rather than hard coding your user
credentials to login with you can call
some services hey you know just create
me a you know a throwaway test account
so we want to make our tests ideally
more data-driven so we can do this
fairly easily with Nightwatch in this
case I'm going to show how you could do
this just by storing the the data for
the test separately from the test itself
so a simple pattern to use is to create
a data directory in your project
directory and then you can a here in
this case I've sort of split it up by
test environment so imagine you have a
dev environment for locally running your
tests and then a staging environment
where you have a staging server set up
to run some final testing before
deploying
so my dev Jas is simply a node module
it's really a simple object where I can
store key value pairs of data that I
want to be able to reference from within
my tests in this case I only have three
values fairly straightforward I'm going
to store my username and password I'm
going to use for the test and I'm going
to store the URL of the login page that
I actually want to navigate to during
the test I have to make one small tweak
to my Nightwatch JS configuration file
to make this work so under the
environment section you can specify a
Global's key and here we just I'm just
requiring that file so I'm setting
Global's to that object basically that
has those values inside of it so one
thing I could do is I might want to
create a separate environment called
staging or something else like that and
then I would require my staging data
file so accessing this data from with
inside of your test is very simple
there's a Global's object that you can
reference from the client object so here
I'm saying
my data is equal to client ID Global's
and now I can just reference that within
the test so I'm using one set one
selecting the URL to go to instead of
that hard-coded string I'm saying data
URL logging which is going to give me
that that string value for me and the
same thing here when I'm filling out my
form so I can say data username and data
dot password to get those values
another thing that's that you can do
that's worth mentioning is you can
actually split up your test into
multiple steps so here I split up my
test into two parts first part I'm
filling out the form and the second part
I'm submitting the form so this might be
interesting to do especially if you have
a very large test suite if there's a lot
a lot of functionality you can split it
up the other key benefit of doing this
is that the entire sequence of steps
with within each section is fully
executed before moving on so this kind
of helps you deal with some of those
asynchronous issues as well so in this
case I'm you know it's in fill out forms
in the fill out form step I'm going to
the web page I was doing a search I'm
filling out the form and then in the
submit form step I'm actually submitting
the form
so this console dot log message won't
actually print out until the entire
previous step is complete so looking at
the output of this it's very similar
it's just that we've now split it up
into two different test tests or test
steps so we have fill out form with the
results and then submit form with the
results
so terminology is pretty simple the
login file is referred to as a test
suite and then each of those sections or
are referred to as tests we have the
Philip form test and the submit form
test another thing that is useful to
know when you're writing tests is what
are your options for checking the state
of the page so we have two AP is we have
assert and verify and they both let you
check if something is true and the key
difference is that a cert will stop the
test if if it fails if the assertion
fails verify won't it will log the
message saying this failed but it will
keep going so depending on your use case
you have these two api's to choose from
another thing that's really important to
know is how do you go ahead and debug
your test so you might write a test and
you expect it to pass but it's just not
passing you can't figure out why there's
a couple of options you can do first
probably one of the most useful API is
is pause so you can call pause on the
client object and this will well pause
the test and leave the browser window
open so you could then go ahead and dig
into dev tools or just you know look at
the page and kind of try to figure out
you know what the heck is going on the
other option is if you're trying to
debug your your test code itself the
probably easiest way to do it in my
opinion is to just use the debugger
statement and then hop into the node
debugger to step through your code if
you're not familiar with a node debugger
you can there's a link at the bottom
where you can look at the API Docs
there's also some instructions on the
Nightwatch website on how to set this up
with webstorm so if you like more of a
visual or GUI debugger you can do that
as well
notice spectacle work as well yep so
there's lots of commands available it
pretty much Maps just standard selenium
API for the most part you can do things
like you know check the attributes get
the attributes on element of course get
title of the page basically inspect
anything about the page that you're
currently looking at
you also have a fair number of
assertions and you can use these with
either the assert or verify method
depending on what you what you what kind
of behavior you want to happen if it
fails you can assert on things like you
know is a attribute on element a certain
value is something hidden is the page
title an expected value is an element on
the page as a not on the page etc so
there's quite a lot of flexibility in in
here between the commands and assertions
however if you need to do something
which is not already supported you can
create your own custom commands and
assertions so here's an example where I
created a somewhat contrived example
creating a custom command so in this
case I'm going to this webpage Netflix
and then take account is a custom
command that I created and basically
what this does is it lets me give a
particular element type or tag in this
case an anchor and then get a result of
happening if those elements are on the
page here I'm defining a custom
assertion so if I want to assert that
there are at least a hundred anchor
elements on the page I could do that
with this API call so this is showing
how to use the custom extensions and
next I'm going to talk about how you
actually implement those
so doing a command I think is arguably
easier than doing an insertion this is
an example of how we would implement our
tag name so essentially all you do is
implement a node module and it takes a
callback and then in this case a value
mapping to the tag name that you want to
check for and so then we just call
execute and what this is doing is saying
I want to execute the following code
within the context of the webpage not
within the node context but within the
actual browser that we're observing
through this test so this is one reason
why I actually prefer writing my
selenium tests in JavaScript because if
you're ever doing if you're ever trying
to inject JavaScript into the page is
much more natural more natural since
you're already writing the tests code
itself in JavaScript versus something
like Python where you're writing in
Python and then you have to sort of
inline some JavaScript it's just
personal preference but anyway so it's
is pretty straightforward so that gets
the values by calling get elements by
tag name and then we're looking at the
length of that value that's returned and
then we call back with the results I
realize this is probably too small for
most of you to see this is an example of
writing a custom assertion as you can
sort of tell from the length of this
slide there's a bit more code you have
to implement to write a custom assertion
is still not too hard and I encourage
you to check out the API Doc's there's a
great talk about how to do this for
yourself additionally at the end of this
talk I'm linked to a github repo that I
put together where you can see all this
sample code that I'm showing you today
so the final step to actually using
these extensions is to hook it up by
referencing them in your Nightwatch
configuration so you just add two new
values custom commands path and custom
assertions path to tell the framework
where your extensions live so there's a
lot more to explore with Nightwatch it
does support before and after test hooks
like most testing frameworks you can
take screenshots as I mentioned before
you can use cloud services such as sauce
labs to actually execute the tests and
you know a whole bunch of other things
to explore so I really encourage you to
try it out if you're at all interested
in functional testing and you know give
back to the community as well so go
ahead and you know I know one user for
example recently wrote a nice
documentation about the using the page
object model with Nightwatch so if you
if you come across something that isn't
documented well or you think could be
explained better you know just write
some documentation that's a great way to
contribute as well and getting started
is really easy like I mentioned before
you just have to install Nightwatch with
NPM of course a prereq to that is having
node installed which is also fairly easy
to get up and running you can then
download the selenium jar separately and
then you configure your Nightwatch
project and you just write some tests
so to make this process even easier I
put together a yeoman generator that you
can grab and that takes care of there's
like a and rapper known modular
rappers that will take care of like
downloading slam jar for you and giving
you a saying default you know Nightwatch
configuration file so if you go ahead
and use this it's like really really
simple just to get up and running and
write some tests so a couple of closing
thoughts this is obviously controversial
perhaps but in my opinion net washe
guess is probably your best option for
doing selenium testing with JavaScript I
would love to be proven wrong if any of
you know of even betting even better
framework I'd love to hear about it I
think it's an area that is valuable to
pursue because one problem a lot of
organizations have is that there are
slam tests over in in Ruby or Python and
that that's a that creates a barrier to
entry for web developers to actually
start helping out a writing test because
they may not know those languages
whereas if we use a language like
JavaScript which are all really familiar
with already is much easier to get
started writing tests like I said before
it's got a really good community a lot
of activity on the github repo and it's
you know really trivial to get started
so go ahead and check it out here are
some resources that you can use to help
you on your journey
there's the guiding API Doc's on the
official website I've got the github
repo for this talk with all the code
samples up there on github as well as
the Nightwatch generator for yeoman and
finally Nightwatch does have
experimental support for a page object
model which i didn't talk about too much
but if you're familiar with selenium
testing in general the main idea behind
a page object model is that you
encapsulate the interaction with a
particular webpage in its own file and
it kind of serves like an api to the
webpage rather than hard coding your CSS
CSS selectors in every single test that
you write you can just include this page
object and say you know like get me
content from search results or something
like that
so check that out the official
documentation doesn't have anything
about the page object model yet it was
in fluent it fairly recently but a user
did go ahead and write some pretty good
documentation which is on a github issue
right now and hopefully Andre will
incorporate that incorporate that back
into the the main documentation site but
you can find that at the last link below
so that's pretty much all I have but I
save time at the end for questions so if
anybody's curious about anything that
I've talked about please feel free to
ask some questions this is just use
webdriver J's yeah good question so for
the communication with selenium does it
use webdriver j/s or another existing
module no it last time I checked it does
not he actually implemented his own
client for the API
and
okay yeah so the question is if you look
at some other frameworks like protractor
how do you decide between that option
versus Nightwatch to be perfectly honest
I haven't looked into protractor too
much if anybody here has experience with
it and can offer some insight on the
kind of pros and cons that'd be great
but I honestly am Not sure my
understanding is that protractor is is
designed to be very very good at testing
angular apps and I assume it'll work
with other apps but I don't really know
general mission is how long's this stuff
circling
require
yep so the I think two questions first
part was about continuous integration
how it integrates with existing services
like Travis and CN circle CI so I've
used it with Travis it seems to work
fine I imagine would be similar
experience with circle
second question was for the global data
or the Global's why do i why did I use
the Global's option in the Nightwatch
config instead of just requiring the
data object directly so one reason is
that you can take advantage of the
concept of different environments more
easily
so in the Nightwatch config you can
unify in this case I just had one
environment the default environment but
you might have you know multiple ones
like staging you know test I don't know
other environments that you wanted to
configure and that just kind of takes
advantage of that existing nomenclature
so I know okay I'm in my my dev
environment because that's been selected
when I invoke the framework and now I
automatically get that data set so
that's the only reason you could totally
just require the object a more
traditional way as well think I solves
that you can basically judge on script
yes yep slow because everytime requests
acids round trip yesterday support
built-in for assertions that you can run
sort of client-side
okay okay yes I think the question was
yeah so I think the question was first
of all performance generally slam tests
yes generally slam tests are relatively
slow as certainly much much much slower
than unit tests Nightwatch tries to help
out with that by allowing you to execute
tests in parallel which helps somewhat I
think the second part of your question
was is there some notion of doing
assertions client side rather than on
the node side in which in which case you
have to kind of cross that barrier to
the client every time you make the
assertion there's not that I know of but
that actually is a really interesting
idea
so have I tested anything caught more
complicated such as drag and drop
you eyes I actually haven't I know that
you can hook up to pretty much any Mouse
event or type of Dom event so in theory
is totally possible I can't really
comment as to how complex it would be
the implement though but that's a good
idea to think about so maybe you should
go home and try it out and then post to
the project I'm sorry for native apps
we're going for Cordova apps not that
I've tried I don't see why it couldn't
work I know that those are the guys at
Yahoo that created a selenium driver for
Cordova I can't remember but I would
imagine that it at the
okay great so you use appium as an
option I'm not I'm not sure but again
try it out cool we have an expert from
sauce labs here so if you have any
questions about sauce
okay well thank you very much I'm going
to stick around for a while so if you
have any other questions