hello and welcome to TechSoup tutorial
today we are going to learn about
promises in JavaScript promises in
JavaScript it's pretty much like
promises in real life your kid makes you
a promise
to clean the room by end of the day
either by end of the day he finishes his
promise by cleaning the room or he fails
in JavaScript promises are similar we
will first look at a simple example of
promise then we will understand why do
we need promises in JavaScript and
lastly we will look at example where you
have dependency where one promise
depends on the second promise to finish
so firstly this is how you define a
promise you would say let this is the
name of my promise equal to new promise
this takes a callback function and this
callback function has two arguments the
first argument is resolved
and the second argument is reject the
resolve really means I am fulfilling
this promise and I'm resolving it means
you finished what you said you have you
would finish reject means promise is not
fulfilled in given time or given
constraint I'm rejecting it so you have
two things either resolve it or reject
inside here you first thing you would do
is because a promise is to clean the
room which means you're going to clean
the room so I'm not going to write how
to clean the room in JavaScript so I'm
just gonna write a comment that cleaning
the room now when the cleaning of the
room is finished I want to set up some
status right so here I'm just gonna
equal to trip is clean if the room is
clean and when I resolve it so simply I
would run the function resolve which is
you know to call my function
mmm else I am going to reject it the
first part is to do what you supposed to
do the promise to do something so you're
going to do that
first and then the second part is to
either resolve or reject when is this
promise the second part is you can
execute this promise this could be
taking a little bit longer time you have
to wait for it and there is a method
that gets called when the promise is
resolved which is call then so when this
method is fired which means the promise
is resolved
so within this method you can have a
callback function and because it's only
executed when the the promises of room
is and then what I can do I can receive
the status back from this resolve
function so here I can just say clean ok
so I can say from resolve which would be
this so when it resolves it would pass
this argument inside this all and when
the promise is fulfilled using then it
will pass this argument which is the
same same guy here clean so I can then
simply say from resolve this so if I run
this I get the room is clean now let's
say if you reject it what would happen
so for that we can chain another
argument called catch here I would pass
a function and I would say from rejected
so here I would have to say not clean
right so if it's clean then it would
resolve it
if it's not clean then it reject it so
if it's going to be rejected I need to
say false here then in that case it
would reject it
and I would get this not clean through
this argument and I can console of it
okay so be the messages the room is not
clean now again here what we promised to
do is happening by the way we're not
doing anything but in order to explain
the concept I wanted to keep it very
clean and assuming that after doing this
is clean a set that makes the promise
either resolve or reject before we move
on I'm saving this example here so if
you go to this particular URL you can
check it out okay
now look at a little bit of complex
example where you have to finish
something before you can start something
right so let's say if you you know you
cannot remove the garbage before you can
actually clean the room see how to clean
the room so once you finish cleaning
your room then you can remove the
garbage and once you you know do both
then you get ice cream
you know your parents would give you ice
cream as an award you cannot get the
reward until you clean the room and take
the garbage so there's dependency right
so here in the code I have three
separate promises basically I have three
functions the first function let the
clean room it actually returns a promise
to clean the room and within I'm
directly resolving it I don't I don't
need to wait for I don't we clean so I'm
just resolving it right away
otherwise you would here you would
basically clean the room and then
resolve it either resolve or reject but
I'm just resolving it mint it clean same
thing happening for remove the garbage
and winning the ice cream okay now I
want to write this nested promise where
once the cleaning is done I want to
remove the garbage and once garbage is
removed I want to get the ice cream okay
so our first right clean the room and
see how the syntax is so nice and this
is why we use promises so I would first
clean the room so when I execute this
function ate nothing but returns this
promise okay that I've defined here and
when as I said before it has a damn
function which actually wait for
promised you finished and only then it
would run this function then now inside
this dent function I would have a
callback function since it only runs
when these this promise is finished then
I can start another promise which is
serial the garbage so all I'm going to
simply do is return garbage now when I
execute this this function it nothing
but it returns this promise and
basically this now became a becomes a
promise for a remove the garbage so I
can actually run then on that promise
within that I have a function that waits
for that promise to finish to remove the
garbage once it's finished I can return
another function call win icecream when
that is done I can simply say I can add
another function side which basically
runs when everything is done all three
promises have been fulfilled here you
would say if I run this
it has finished actually since for every
resolve I am getting a message back into
this dent functions because when I
finished cleaning the room it sends a
message with the resolve call clean the
room I can actually catch this message
in a result and I can pass that message
into the next function when I same thing
I would get a result here as well and I
can pass it here and in the end I would
get a result here as well
now what I can do I can whatever message
that I get in the first after cleaning
the room message and I can append this
message so what is going to do is going
to can get all the messages resulting
from fulfilling the each promises oh and
actually I need to say finished plus if
I run this it says finished clean the
room remove a garbage one ice cream
all three done and you can see it
happened in that sequence because of
this dependency so this is how you can
actually put the dependency and you can
see how clean this code is compared to
if you were to use a simple callback
function to do this without using
promises you will have one function
where you you have to nest everything
and if you have like a so many callback
function it becomes a nightmare so
promises at least solves this problem
because you can independently define
these promises and then when you resolve
it it's also quite clean now I have
saved this example in this URL so if you
want to play around with it you can load
this I will also provide the link in the
YouTube video as well now let's say if
you want to do all these in parallel
with you don't want to wait for one to
finish and second to start you just want
them all three promises spawn at the
same time and you want once all of them
are done you want to do something so for
that I will do something like this I
would say promise dot all and inside I
will pass an array with all three
promises so I would clean the room
remove the garbage and when ice cream
and they will all finish I would have it
then and here I would have the callback
function
I'll finish when I run this gives me the
result back says it's all finished but
let's say instead of waiting for all the
finish what if you just want one of them
to finish any of them then you want to
do something for that you would use
instead of all you would say please you
would take race the de log would fire up
and say one of them is finished
let's see you three server with the same
data and you try to pull for redundancy
and as soon as the first one shows up
you are satisfied because you got the
data right you don't want to wait for
the other two to finish right in that
case you would use this then it comes
back with one of them is finished anyway
so that's one of the promises I promise
this tutorial and I deliver it so please
resolve it if you liked the tutorial
please give a comment like it and
subscribe thank you
you